<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>meta &#8211; Saki&#039;s Romhacking Shenanigans</title>
	<atom:link href="https://sakimotor.github.io/category/meta/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://sakimotor.github.io</link>
	<description>It is what it is!</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 11:22:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Welcome to Saki&#8217;s &#8220;Romhacking&#8221; dumpsterfire!</title>
		<link>https://sakimotor.github.io/2023/01/24/welcome-to-sakis-romhacking-dumpsterfire/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[sakicore]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 00:37:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[meta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[intro]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://sakimotor.github.io/?p=8</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A short story about me, my passions, and the purpose of this blog.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hello there. If you&#8217;re reading this without knowing me yet, I&#8217;m <strong>Saki</strong>, a (as of this post) 21 year old French guy with a fair amount of knowledge when it comes to programming (<em>C, Java, Python</em> and even a slight amount of <em>assembly</em>) and, most importantly, someone who&#8217;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCsIqSsvvtAXmF8X9Lcx9tYg" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCsIqSsvvtAXmF8X9Lcx9tYg"><em>really </em>into video game music</a>.  Why specify that for a blog (supposedly) about <em>romhacking </em>? The answer to that is easier than you might think!</p>



<p>First of all, a lot of games tend to not have an official album with their soundtrack released at all, no matter how famous the compositions might be. Take <a href="https://vgmdb.net/forums/showthread.php?t=1977" data-type="URL" data-id="https://vgmdb.net/artist/1301">Ecco The Dolphin: Defender Of The Future</a> as an example: the game is widely-known for its gorgeous compositions made by Tim Follin &amp; Attila Heger, yet we are still to have an official release, truly a shame. </p>



<p>Secondly, some games had a <em>soundtrack</em> released, but it was unfortunately not faithful to how it sounded ingame. This is a common occurence with the old releases, such as the Namco GSM collections, or even the obscure Amiga shoot&#8217;em&#8217;up <a href="https://vgmdb.net/album/42332" data-type="URL" data-id="https://vgmdb.net/album/42332">Apidiya </a>(how Techno Party sounds on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q3Ps3d-JiOg">album</a> vs how it sounds <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=57YNerorom8" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=57YNerorom8">ingame</a>, not quite the same).</p>



<p>As such,  it is common for game music to <em>Gamerip</em>, or simply put get a game&#8217;s music straight from its files, in order to have the faithful sound. This process is rarely a straightforward one, especially when it comes ot old and/or console games, which almost never leave the audio files in plain sight, but use either archives or proprietary audio codecs instead, either to optimize on space or to obfuscate the data,<em> probably both</em>. That&#8217;s when the <em>romhacking</em>/<em>reverse-engineering</em> part comes in!</p>



<p>Since the used file formats are proprietary, and usually not readable as is, a great amount of effort has been put by numerous people throught time in order to document said formats, and come up with <em>tools</em> that can read the data, and even convert it to more common formats. Take the <em>Super Nintendo</em>&#8216;s .<em><a href="http://www.vgmpf.com/Wiki/index.php?title=SPC">SPC </a></em>format, which is conceptually not unlike a .<em>MIDI </em>file (don&#8217;t take my words on that, I&#8217;m not a musician nor a sound engineer). The format has been documented so much that it is now possible to read the audio on your own computer by using one of the dozens of available <a href="http://snesmusic.org/v2/players.php" data-type="URL" data-id="http://snesmusic.org/v2/players.php"><em>tools</em> </a>, even though you don&#8217;t even <em>own</em> an SNES!</p>



<p>Lastly, I felt the need to mention I&#8217;m <em>French</em>. Why that ? Once again, the answer is not hard! </p>



<p>When I play some games, mostly English ones but sometimes Japanese as well ( I don&#8217;t speak that language unfortunately), the thought &#8220;<em>hmmmm I wish this was translated in French&#8221;</em> often comes to my mind. For japanese games with voice acting, I also often think about making <em>undubbed</em> versions on their western counterparts (i.e modifying the game to use the japanese voices as it wasn&#8217;t a standard until the <em>late-PS3</em> era). Because of that, I&#8217;ve looked unto various games, various file formats, by using a plethora of tools available on <em><a href="https://zenhax.com/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://zenhax.com/">ZenHax</a>, <a href="https://forum.xentax.com/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://forum.xentax.com/">Xentax</a>, <a href="https://www.romhacking.net/">ROMhacking.ne</a></em><a href="https://www.romhacking.net/"><em>t</em></a> and whatnot, sometimes with mitigated success, but mostly with complete failure at the end of the day.</p>



<p>However! All is not to throw away! Even if I didn&#8217;t manage to obtain the results I wanted, I still got to familiarize myself with a plethora of <em>romhacking</em> tools that might end being of use someday, either by myself (once I&#8217;ve acquired enough patience and experience), or someone else, who might be more competent, more patient, or simply more stubborn than me.</p>



<p>Such is the purpose of this blog: talking about some tools I used, the way they are supposed to be used and what can be done with them. Prepare for some <strong>action </strong>(and some ranting), we&#8217;re going to <strong>break through</strong> the formats! (<em>mostly with preexisting tools, but the day might come when I&#8217;ll reverse a format by myself&#8230;)</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
